I can see it.
見える
I'm fine.
大丈夫だ
I can dodge it if I watch closely.
よく見てけばかわせる。
If I don't get hit,
it doesn't matter what weapon he uses.
当たらなきゃ…どんな武器もないのと同じだ…！
Yeah!
シャッ！
Nice, kid!
いいぞコゾー！
You can do it!
がんばれー！
That kid's pretty good!
やるのぅあのチビ！
He was able to hit the captain.
大将に一撃入れたぞ！
Quick guys like him are tough!
ああいうはしっこいのはしぶといぜ！
This could turn out to be a good fight!
久々にいい勝負が見られるか！？
Damn! I can't cut him.
He's wearing chain mail underneath.
クソ！斬れねェ…下に鎖かたびらを着てやがる
Too bad, I liked these.
これ気に入ってたのに～
So, you're not afraid of my ax?
ウム！オレの斧を恐れないか。
You have a lot of guts. You're just like Thors.
度胸はまずまず。そのへんはトールズゆずりだな
You big bastard. Who are you to my father?
デカブツてめぇ…父上のなんなんだ？
He didn't tell you? That's so cold of him.
お前なんも聞いてないの？あいつも薄情だなァ
I heard he's descended from a jarl.
He was of noble origin.
もとはヤルル…高貴な出だと聞いてる
Helga's the one from a family of jarls.
ヤルルなのはヘルガの血筋だ。
Thors rose through the ranks
because of his skill with the sword.
トールズは剣の腕で成り上がったのさ
What?
なに…？
Do you want to know more?
もっと聞きたい？
Do you?
聞きたい？
If you want me to tell you,
聞きたかったらな。
you'll have to entertain me some more.
もう少しオレを楽しませることだぜ。
All right, Thorfinn?
なァ！トルフィン
I can entertain you.
楽しませてやってもいいけどな。
But it's going to be hard holding back enough
to make sure you can still talk.
口が利ける程度に手加減すんのは難しいぜ
Do you know what you're saying, kid?
言うねーコゾー！
My stomach hurts!
ハラいてー！
Holding back on the captain? You?
大将に手加減するとさあのチビ！
Go easy on us!
お手柔らかにー！
You're an idiot! You're an idiot!
アホや！アホや！
Was that funny?
おかしいか？
I consider Thorfinn to be a warrior.
トルフィンは俺の認めた戦士だ。
Don't laugh!
笑うな！
Thors was stronger than me.
トールズはオレより強かった！
Prove to me that you really are Thors' child,
自分がまさしくトールズの子だと証明してみせろ！
Thorfinn!
トルフィン！
That stupid kid. He came back here to die.
バカガキめ…死にに戻ってきやがって…
What happened to the prince?
王子はどうなってやがる…
Hey! Over there! Go!
Hold down his leg!
OUT OF THE CRADLE
Do the same over there!
I can hear the sound the of battle nearby.
近くで…戦の声がする…
Stop it already!
ああ…もういいかげんにしてくれ…
Don't you have anything better to do?
他にすることはないのか？
Be quiet!
静かにしてくれ…
I don't want to open my eyes.
目を開けたくないんだ…
I want to stay asleep...
このまま寝ていたい…
like this... forever.
このまま…ずっと…
Your Highness... Your Highness...
Your Highness Canute.
殿下…殿下…クヌート殿下…
Ragnar! You're still alive--
ラグナル…！お前、生きて…
This is a dream, isn't it, Ragnar?
これは…夢なのだな？ラグナル…
Yes. I came to say goodbye.
はい。お別れを申し上げに参りました
Are you going? You'll leave me behind?
逝くのか…僕を残して…
Are you telling me to live alone in a world like this?
僕ひとりで…こんな世界で生きてゆけというのか。
Do you think I can survive?
生きてゆけると思うのか…
I...
私めは…
failed as the person tasked
with your education.
あなた様の教育係として失格でした
I was supposed to raise you as a jarl.
But I raised you as a normal child,
あなた様をヤルルとしてではなく、ごく普通の…
like a farmer would raise his own child.
それこそ農民が我が子を育てるがごとくにして参りました
Even though I knew that's not what the king wanted.
Please forgive me.
それが陛下のお望みではないと知りつつ…おゆるし下さい…
What's wrong with that? You understood my feelings
better than my father, the king!
何がいけないのだ！
お前は父王陛下より僕自身の望みを汲んでくれた！
I never wanted to be born into the royal family.
王家になど…生まれたくなかった…
If I had been...
お前の子に…
If I had been born as your son,
僕はっ！お前の子に生まれていたら…
everything would have been better.
どんなに…よかったかと…
Your Highness.
殿下…！
I'm so happy, Your Highness.
うれしゅうございます…殿下…！
Don't go. I love you.
いかないで…お前が好きなんだ…
There are some things that you only realize
once you've experienced a loss.
失って識ることがございます。
You've noticed already.
あなた様はすでにお気づきでしょう
Ragnar...
ラグナル…
I'm just a dream.
私めのことは夢でございます
Wait...
待て…
The time for you to awake has come.
もはや目覚める時が来たのです
No... Ragnar!
いやだ…ラグナル…
Come back!
戻れっ…
戻れ！
I wish you well, Your Highness.
お健やかに。殿下…
Ragnar...
ラグナル…
Don't be afraid! Attack together!
ビビるなァ！一斉にかかれ！！
Are you hurt anywhere?
お体、痛みはございませんか？
Those men are fighting over you.
あの者たちは、殿下を得ようと争っているのです。
The winner is going to take you.
あなたは勝者のものになります
You're a priest. Aren't you going
to stop them from fighting?
神父であろうそなた。争いを止めぬのか？
Is there a way to stop them? It's better
to let those who wish to die, die.
止めようがありますか？死にたい者は死なせてやればよいのです
I had a dream.
夢を見た。
It was a dream about Ragnar.
ラグナルの夢だ
He said goodbye.
別れを告げられた。
He was a faithful man, even in death.
死んでまで律儀な男だ
In this world...
もうこの地上に…
there's no one who loves me anymore.
私を愛してくれる者はいなくなった
You've found enlightenment. But you're wrong.
それは大いなる悟りです。だが惜しい。
Was the emotion that Ragnar felt towards you love?
ラグナル殿のあなたへの思いは…愛ですか？
In order to keep you safe,
彼はあなたの安全のために、
he watched as 62 innocent villagers were killed.
62人の善良な村人を見殺しにした
Your Highness.
殿下。
Love...
愛とは
What is it?
なんですか？
But you know, these guys weren't that good.
しっかしよォ。手応えなかったなァこいつら
It's not easy to find strong opponents.
強ェ奴らにお目にかかるのは難しいよ。
We'll never get to Valhalla.
いつまでたってもヴァルハラに行けやしねェ
Is the captain's duel still going on?
まだ大将の決闘続いてんのか？
No way. He should have killed him instantly.
まさか。秒殺だろ
Then what are they so excited about?
ならなんであんなに盛り上がってんだよ
I'll go check.
お…オレ見てくるわ！
Me too.
あぁオレも！
Hey! What's going on?
オイオイどーなってんだよ！？
Kill him!
殺っちめー！
Captain!
大将ー！
You kid!
てめェコゾー！
Stop running away!
逃げんなー！
Impossible!
マジかよ。
How could the captain...?
あの大将が…
He's getting beaten up by that kid!
やられっぱなしじゃねーか！あんな小僧に！！
Nice, Thorfinn!
いいぞトルフィン！
I don't even have five men who'd be a match for you!
お前にかなう奴ァオレの手下に5人といないだろう
It's the same chain mail as before.
前と同じ鎖かたびらか…
I should aim for tendons in his arms and legs.
手足の腱を狙うのは有効だ。
I tried to go after his vitals in London,
and I paid the price.
ロンドンでは急所狙いで踏み込んで痛い目を見た。
I can deliver the final blow once I stop him from moving.
とどめはヤツの動きを止めてからだ
However, I know you're strong,
but your swordsmanship
だがなぁ…確かに強いが、お前の剣は…
is, well, only average.
なんかこー…フツ～ってカンジ？
There's still something missing
before you achieve perfection as a warrior.
戦士として完成するには何かが足りない
If that's the case, then,
why are you having a hard time?
ならそいつ相手にコテンパンのてめェはなんなんだよ
Good point.
そうさ。
I'm missing something, too.
オレにも足りない。
I thought perhaps I could learn it from you,
since you're Thors' child.
トールズの子のお前からならそれを学べると思ってたんだが…
Hey, Thorfinn.
なァ。トルフィンよ。
What do you think?
お前はどう思う
What does it mean
本当の戦士って
to be a true warrior?
なんだ？
Are you asking what love is?
愛とはなにか…だと？
Are you saying that Ragnar didn't love me?
ラグナルは私を愛していなかったというのか？
Yes.
はい
Then let me ask you.
ならば問うのは私のほうだ。
If what Ragnar felt wasn't love,
ラグナルに愛がないのなら、
then who can embody love correctly?
正しく愛を体現できる者はどこにいるのだ
He's right there.
そこに居ますよ。
See?
ホラ
When he died, he became more beautiful
than anyone among the living.
彼は死んで、どんな生者よりも美しくなった。
He's love itself.
愛そのものといっていい
He'll never hate others or steal anymore.
彼はもはや、憎むことも奪うこともしません
He was abandoned there.
彼はこのままここに打ち捨てられ、
He's going to give his body with generosity
to the beasts and the insects.
その肉を獣や虫に惜しみなく与えるでしょう
He lies exposed to the wind and the rain,
雨風にさらされるがまま、
but won't speak a single word in complaint.
それで一言半句の文句も言いません
Death...
死は…
perfects a person.
人間を完成させるのです
Hey!
Do it! Come on!
Damn!
クソッ！
So, you don't know?
わからんか…
Don't worry about it.
I wasn't expecting you to know anyway.
まァ気にすんなよ。そんなには期待してなかった
That was dirty!
姑息な手を！
Are you saying that death is the essence of love?
愛の本質が…死だというのか
Yes.
はい
Then what is the feeling when parents
care for their children,
ならば親が子を…夫婦が互いを、
when a husband and wife care for each other,
and when Ragnar cares about me?
ラグナルが私を大切に思う気持ちは一体なんだ？
It's discrimination.
差別です。
It's no different from fawning over a king
while hitting a slave with a whip.
王にへつらい奴隷に鞭打つことと、たいして変わりません
To Ragnar, you were more important
than anyone else, Your Highness.
ラグナル殿にとって、王子殿下は他の誰よりも大切な人だったのです。
Probably even more important than his own life.
おそらく彼自身の命よりも…
His tender feelings towards you were discrimination.
彼の…あなたに対する心弱い思いは…差別です
I see.
そうか…
I'm beginning to understand.
わかってきた…
I feel like
まるで…
the fog has lifted.
霧が晴れていくようだ…
What?
あれ？
Come on!
だーもーっ！
He's done with you!
見切られてるぞ！
Hey...
ぬう…
Damn... It's still too shallow.
クソッ！まだ浅い！
I'm beginning to understand.
わかってきた
This snow...
この雪が…
is love, right?
愛、なのだな…
That's right.
そうです
The sky.
あの空が…
The sun.
あの太陽が…
The wind.
吹きゆく風が…
The fog.
木々が…
The mountains.
山々が…！
But then...
なのに…
I can't believe it.
なんということだ…
The world.
世界が…
The creation of God is so beautiful.
But then why...
神の御技がこんなにも美しいというのに…
is there no love...
人間の心には…
in the hearts of men?
愛がないのか
They say that the reason we turned into
creatures like this
私たちがこのような生き物になってしまったのは…
is because our ancestors disobeyed God
遠い祖先が神に背き、
and committed a sin long ago.
罪を犯したせいだといわれています
We were...
私たちは…
expelled from paradise.
楽園から追放されたのです
What?
あれ？おい！
Where did he go?
どこ行った？
Hey. What's that?
おい！アレって…
He dampened the shock with his legs. Nice move.
足のバネで衝撃を殺したか！やるね！
Over there!
あそこだ！
Wow!
すげー！
He must be dead now!
ありゃ死んだろー！？
Impressive, captain!
さすが大将！
Damn.
クソ…
I've lost all hope now.
いよいよ万策尽きたか…
It looks like the battle is over.
決着がついたようですね。
But
だが…
this is no good. That man has gone insane.
いけませんな。あの者は正気を失っている
Your Highness. You had better run away.
殿下。お逃げになったほうがよいでしょう
Sane?
正気？
Is anyone sane in this world?
正気の人間が、この世のどこにいるのだ。
Everyone's the same.
みな同じ…
みな同じだ。
No one knows how to love.
誰もが等しく、愛することを知らぬのであろうが
No one knows the meaning of life.
生の意味を知らず、
No one knows the meaning of death.
死の意味を知らず、
No one even knows the reason they're fighting.
己の戦う意味さえも知らぬ
Your Highness.
殿下
I've had enough. I'm sick of it.
もういい。もううんざりだ
What we lost in exchange for wisdom...
智を得て、かわりに失ったもの…
The most important thing... It's something
最も大切なもの…そしてそれは
that we'll never get back as long as we live.
生ある限り、私たちの手には入らぬもの
We'll never attain it.
手には入らぬ。
Yet, even then...
それでも…
You still tell us to seek it?
それでも追い求めよというのか！
Father in heaven!
天の父よ！
Miserable warrior.
あわれな戦士。
You're the farthest from love.
最も愛より遠き者
You, who have been expelled from paradise.
楽園を追われし者よ
Isn't there any way to end the suffering
from your punishment other than death?
そなたたちの罰の苦しみは、死より他に終わらせるすべがないのか！？
Are you saying that we only exist
so that we may be tested and endure?
我々の生は！試され、耐え続けるためにのみあるというのか！
Father in heaven!
天の父よ！
This man's soul cannot be saved
through the trials you set for him!
あなたの与える試練では、この者の魂は救えぬ！
Father.
父よ…
I no longer seek your salvation.
もはやあなたの救いは求めぬ
If you will no longer give us salvation,
あなたが与えてくれぬなら…
then, with our own hands,
我々の手で！
on this earth,
この地上に…
we shall create our own paradise.
再びの楽園を…！
What? Prince?
あれ？王子？
Ow!
いッてエェエエ！
Prince! Are you okay?
王子！無事か！？
Stop, you fools.
やめんか馬鹿者！
Don't fight futile battles anymore.
これ以上無益な争いをするな！
Futile?
むっ無益！？
Your wounds are deep. Are you okay?
深手だな。大丈夫か？
Damn. I slipped up.
くそっ…ぬかったぜ…！
Don't move. Your stomach is cut. Willibald!
動くな。腹をやられている。ヴィリヴァルド！！
Treat his wounds.
この者の手当てをしておけ。
I'm going to catch the horses.
私は散った馬を捕まえる。
You. Help him.
そなた、手伝え
Your Highness, I've seen a miracle.
殿下…私は…奇跡を見ました
Be quiet and treat his wounds.
黙って手当てにかかれ！
Hey! Prince! Where are you going?
お、おい！ちょっ王子！どこ行く気だよ！？
We're going to give you to Thorkell!
Or else my buddies--
あんたはトルケル軍に引き渡す！でないとオレの仲間が…！
I was already planning to see Thorkell.
もとよりトルケルの所へ行くつもりだ。
We won't be able to transport the wounded
unless we borrow their sleds.
連中にソリを借りねば、そのケガ人は運べぬ
What? You're talking nonsense!
なっ…！寝言ぬかすんじゃねーぞ！
Do you have any idea why I'm in
such a mess right now? You idiot!
何のためにズタボロんなったと思ってんだボケ！
If you get captured by Thorkell,
then there will be no meaning to any of this!
テメェがトルケルに捕まっちまったら…意味ねーんだよッ！
Meaning?
意味？
Did you say meaning?
意味だと？
The meaning of your battles?
そなたたちの戦いのか？
There is no meaning to a battle like this.
こんな戦いに意味などない。
So, don't die.
だからもう死ぬな
Warriors. Become my vassals.
戦士たちよ。私の家臣になれ。
I shall teach you about when you must fight,
and against whom.
戦わねばならぬ時と相手を…教えてやろう
I shall give meaning to your battles.
To your life and death.
そなたたちの戦いに、生と死に。意味を与えてやろう
That's what...
それが…
the duty of a king is.
王の務めだ